<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Web and Biology | Schmidtyworks</title>
    <description>My thoughts on land management as a wildlife biologist for the Bereau of Land Management. 
</description>
    <link>//</link>
    <atom:link href="//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 09:53:32 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 09:53:32 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Big Sagebrush</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had to do some research on big sagebrush (&lt;em&gt;Artemisia tridentata&lt;/em&gt;) subspecies for a project that I am working on.  Here’s a little key to the important subspecies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Wyoming Big Sagebrush&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;blog-post-icon&quot;&gt;Scientific Name&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Artemesia tridentata wyomingensis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;blog-post-icon&quot;&gt;Soils&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;frigid, mesic, and xeric soils of silty, clayey, skeletal, and mixed textures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;soil pH ranges from moderately acidic to moderately basic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;blog-post-icon&quot;&gt;Precipitation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;greater than 7 inches (200 mm) of annual precipitation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where the ranges of Wyoming and mountain big sagebrush overlap, Wyoming big sagebrush generally occurs where precipitation is less than 12 inches (300 mm), whereas mountain big sagebrush occurs on wetter sites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;sagebrush-states&quot;&gt;

  &lt;h3&gt;Elevation&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;ul class=&quot;elevation-list&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;up to 7,260 feet (2200 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;M &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Idaho--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2,500 to 6,500 feet (700-1980 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;r &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Utah--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;5,030 to 6,530 feet (1525-1980 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;x &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Wyoming--&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;5,000 to 7,000 feet (1500-2100 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;F &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Colorado--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;below 7,000 feet (2100 m)(Colorado)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arttriw/all.html&quot;&gt;USDA Plants Database - Wyoming Big Sagebrush&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Mountain Big Sagebrush&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Artemesia tridentata vaseyana&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Soils
* Soils are moderately deep, well-drained, slightly acid to slightly alkaline and characterized by late-melting winter snow cover and summer moisture
* In a landscape-scale study in Wyoming, soils in topographic depressions occupied by mountain big sagebrush had higher organic matter, nutrients and microbial biomass than soils in more exposed (windblown) areas occupied by other vegetation, including basin and Wyoming big sagebrush. The effect was attributed to greater snow accumulation, leading to greater plant and litter biomass accumulation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Precipitation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;although mountain big sagebrush is the most common sagebrush in the Great Basin pinyon-juniper woodlands, only the wettest and coolest areas of the higher and larger mountain passes have mountain big sagebrush in their woodlands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;sagebrush-states&quot;&gt;

  &lt;h3&gt;Elevation&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;ul class=&quot;elevation-list&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!-- Californai --&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;5,905 to 9,840 feet (1,800-3,000 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;M &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Idaho--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2,560 to 8,990 feet ( 780-2,740 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;r &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Utah--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;4,690 to 8,990 feet (1,430-2,740 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;x &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Wyoming--&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;7,250 to 8,040 feet (2,210-2,450 m)(Wyoming)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;F &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Colorado--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;7,760 to 8,480 feet (2,365-2,585 m)(Colorado)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;D &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Arizona--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;4,500 to 7,400 feet (1,370-2,255 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;Z &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Montana--&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;3,770 to 7,810 feet (1,150-2,380 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;g &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Nevada--&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;5,445 to 10,170 feet (1,660-3,100 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

   &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;k &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Oregon--&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;3,500 to 9,000 feet (1,066-2,740 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;


  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arttriv/all.html&quot;&gt;USDA Plants Database - Mountain Big Sagebrush&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Mountain Big Sagebrush&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Artemesia tridentata tridentata&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Soils
* It commonly grows on well-drained soils in valley bottoms, lower foothill areas or in areas adjacent to drainages. Basin big sagebrush is associated with deep, seasonally dry, well-drained soils on plains, valleys, and foothills
* It frequently coincides with high water tables or deep moisture accumulations
* occurs on stratified sandy loam soils on floodplains or on low stream terraces
* In southeastern Idaho, basin big sagebrush is most abundant on sandy soils or at the sandy end of a soil texture gradient
* Basin big sagebrush is considered intolerant of alkaline conditions, but some ecotypes do grow in association with salt-tolerant plants such as shadscale (Atriplex confertifolia), black greasewood (Sarcobatus vermiculatus), and saltgrass (Distichlis spp.)
* In Utah sites occupied by basin big sagebrush tend to be slightly alkaline whereas those occupied by mountain big sagebrush tend to be slightly acidic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Precipitation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basin big sagebrush grows in relatively more mesic habitats than other subspecies of big sagebrush&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Precipitation on basin big sagebrush sites ranges from 10 to 18 inches (250-460 mm) per year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;sagebrush-states&quot;&gt;

  &lt;h3&gt;Elevation&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;ul class=&quot;elevation-list&quot;&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;r &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Utah--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2,001-7,019 feet (610-2140 m) in northeaster Utah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;D &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Arizona--&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;4,800-5,800 feet (1463-1768 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

   &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;stateface&quot;&gt;k &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Oregon--&gt; 
  &lt;p&gt;100-7,000 feet (30-2134 m)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;


  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arttrit/all.html&quot;&gt;USDA Plants Database - Basin Big Sagebrush&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Howard, Janet L. 1999. Artemisia tridentata subsp. wyomingensis. In: Fire Effects Information System, [Online]. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station, Fire Sciences Laboratory (Producer). Available: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/&quot;&gt;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/&lt;/a&gt; [2016, February 19].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Tirmenstein, D. 1999. Artemisia tridentata subsp. tridentata. In: Fire Effects Information System, [Online]. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station, Fire Sciences Laboratory (Producer). Available: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arttrit/all.html&quot;&gt;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/shrub/arttrit/all.html&lt;/a&gt; [2016, February 19].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Johnson, Kathleen A. 2000. Artemisia tridentata subsp. vaseyana. In: Fire Effects Information System, [Online]. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station, Fire Sciences Laboratory (Producer). Available: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/&quot;&gt;http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/&lt;/a&gt; [2016, February 19].&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2016/01/30/Sagebrush.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2016/01/30/Sagebrush.html</guid>
        
        <category>Tech</category>
        
        <category>Note</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Goals 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been contributing to this blog for a little over a year now.  My first post was in September of 2014, and it laid out some goals. I’d like to look back at what I have done so far, see if I have met my goals, and make some goals for 2016 to keep me motivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-i-do&quot;&gt;How did I do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.schmidtyworks.com/blog/2014/09/24/Why-am-i-blogging.html&quot;&gt;that I set&lt;/a&gt;  were for the end of 2014, and on those, I’m at least a year late. But that’s OK. This year I had a ton of stuff going on.  So the fact that I made time to contribute at all was good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My first goal was to finish the site&lt;/strong&gt; and I did.  It isn’t everything I want yet, but it looks pretty good. I’m also proud that it’s completely responsive. Responsive means it will look good on any site. I was also excited that I built it with Jekyll, a static site generator, something that I had never done before.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My second goal was to start creating posts that would be useful for my job&lt;/strong&gt;.  I did pretty well with this one too.  One of the blog posts I wrote, NEPA, helped me answer a question in an interview that led to a promotion.  Check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My third goal was to add a comments section to the site&lt;/strong&gt; I  completed this one as well. Unfortunately I didn’t get the comments to work on the home page, something I’d like to get done this year. I’ll address that later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not bad for my first year. Definitely more to do though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Now What&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not the most goal oriented person.  That sounds kind of bad (is this guy lazy or what).  I just like to go with the flow more and capitalize on opportunities as they come rather than picking something and trying to accomplish it. But being opportunistic only works up to a point.  A consequence of me being opportunistic is I have way too much going on.  I end up trying to do more than I’m capable of and not being particularly proficient at anything. I’d like to narrow my focus a bit by setting some goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Goal 1: Write a blog post a month. 
Pretty self explanatory.  I’ve been at almost one post every two months over the last year or so. I’d like to double that.  This will be one. I have 11 to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Goal 2:  Write more about the technical aspects of my job.
I’ve learned so much over the last year that I can’t even come close to remembering it all. I want to use this site to synthesize what I have learned.  So far on this site, I’ve been writing about big topics like NEPA and the Endangered Species Act.  Don’t get me wrong, I think that those are great topics and I’ve learned a lot writing about them. I think it would be mores useful if I took on specific subjects that I could refer to in the future as references.  There’s so much information out there on wildlife, but it’s all over the place.  Everyday I search the same things over and over again, looking for information that I have already found.  I use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.evernote.com&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt; to try and organize useful information that I find. Thats  useful.  But my notes are always a little sloppy and I never have a chance to look over my notes after I write them. They could use some clean up.  The ultimate goal is to take pages from Evernote and create pages that act as a well organized reference. With links to useful information and an annotated bibliography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I’m still working on how to make this work. But I think its a good idea to try and pursue. I think that it can help me learn and create something useful for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Goal 3: I want to expand who reads this blog. 
I don’t know how to do this yet. One problem is that I’m little too apprehensive about sharing the site.  Part of the problem is that I don’t have a lot of confidence as a writer. The only way to get better is to write, write a lot, and then have people tell you what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goal-4-wordpress&quot;&gt;Goal 4: Wordpress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d like to have this site on wordpress instead of jekyll.  Jekyll is nice for a lot of reasons, but its hard to access at work or on another computer. It’s also harder for me to build repeatable sections that can be reused.  I’ve also had much more experience with wordpress, so it’ll be easier to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Goal 5: Graphs and Charts
I love graphs and charts, but I don’t have any idea about how to display them on the web. I want to make one graph or chart this year and put it up on the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Goal 6:  I will not take on any other web clients.&lt;br /&gt;
I have a habit of giving myself too much work to do.  This year, I tried to take on one web client and I did a terrible job on her site because I was too busy.  No more of that. I’d like to try and focus this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty simple.  Six goals for 2016. Let’s see how I do.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2016/01/02/Goals-2016.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2016/01/02/Goals-2016.html</guid>
        
        <category>Goals</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Get a Permanent Job with the Federal Government</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Working for a federal land management agency is awesome. Managing lands for the people is one of the most rewarding things that a person can do.  If you are fortunate enough to get in as a seasonal it can be frustratingly hard to get into a permanent position. As someone who has made the journey I thought I’d share a little on what I’ve learned about the process.  Don’t get me wrong, I was really lucky. But I don’t think that it was all luck (just mostly) this post is about what I’ve seen work for others and also some things I think I did right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##I Don’t Really Know
There’s no formula for getting a permanent job. There’s no way to work the system, and it is damn hard to get any federal job, let alone a permanent one.  I work with so many talented, highly skilled people that the Feds would be lucky to have in their permanent ranks. Alas, though, the permanent job is a very illusive thing and some, although doing everything right, have not gotten picked up on the permanent train to no fault of their own. They just haven’t been in the right place at they right time yet.  But many others have done a lot to prevent themselves from moving up the chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Move Somewhere that No One wants to Live
It seems like the easiest way to get picked up is to move east or to Nevada; or anywhere that people don’t want to live. There’s no better way to get a great federal job than moving somewhere where you will have less competition for your job. It’s also a lot easier to get work in a place where people don’t want to stick around.  In really desirable locations, people tend to stick around, making openings sparse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see great BLM jobs in Winnemucca, Nevada come up all the time.  And I completely understand why someone would want to avoid Winnemucca. But the areas around Winnemucca are stunning(there are more mountain ranges in Nevada than any other state).  Indeed, some of the most impressive, epic and badass areas are in places that no one wants to live.  If you don’t believe me, take a drive down highway 50 in Nevada.  It has to be one of the most stunning highways in the American west. If you like solitude, don’t move to Colorado, Utah or California move to Nevada, northern New Mexico, Idaho, Wyoming or North Dakota. Also remember that good management of the obscure lands is just as important, if not more important, than those that are more coveted by the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img sizes=&quot;100vw&quot; alt=&quot;black rock desert cars&quot; src=&quot;/images/post-images/permenant_job/blackrock_pano_large.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/permenant_job/blackrock_pano_large.jpg 1500w, /images/post-images/permenant_job/blackrock_pano_medium.jpg 1000w, /images/post-images/permenant_job/blackrock_pano_small.jpg 700w, /images/post-images/permenant_job/blackrock_pano_xsmall.jpg 500w&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;Black Rock Desert site of the famous Burning Man Festival. Photo:me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Stick Around
I thought when I graduated that I had done my learning.  I hadn’t. High school, undergraduate  or graduate school don’t teach you crap about the real world, they teach you how to learn and how to cope with doing new things regularly.  It is impossible to learn everything that you need to for a job in an academic setting.  Will you learn work ethic? Yes. Will you learn how to work a lot? Maybe. Will you learn the basics of a major? Yes? Will you be an expert? Not even close.  There is no way to become an expert in a field until you’ve done it for at the very least a decade.  Even then there will always be something to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, college is particularly bad at preparing you for federal jobs.  Not that you don’t need to learn the science behind your field - school is great at teaching you that - it’s the bureaucracy.  Only the government has governmental bureaucracy at a level that will make you tear your hair out.  On the job training can teach you how to manage both your work, the lack of funding and the millions of trainings that you are required to take annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you learn from supervisors will be invaluable in your future career.  Only those that have walked through the fire can tell you what color and how hot the fire actually is.  I can’t count how many times I’ve come into a situation where I had a plan and was ready to execute when my boss laid out a much simpler way to complete something. So stick around. You’ll thank your older self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##People Leave Faster than You Would Think
To be fair, I didn’t really stick around in Colorado because I wanted to.  I stuck around because I had a girlfriend here that I loved and I didn’t want to leave her.  I was lucky though because everyone that I worked with eventually left, finding a better job somewhere else.  If I hadn’t had someone to stick around for I would have done the same, but I did stick around, and after four years of waiting,  my boss left. And then I stayed around for another three years and my boss left again.   In 7 years I had moved from a seasonal GS-4 to a permanent, professional series, GS-9 wildlife biologist with no masters degree. I was lucky (damn lucky!) but I believe I gave myself a good chance of getting a permanent job because the people hiring me knew and liked me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Did I Mention Luck
Not everyone is lucky.  I’ve seen it happen over and over again.  Someone works their ass off, puts in their time, and becomes very proficient at their job and a job opens up and they get passed over. For no good reason. And it sucks. But it will probably happen to you. So do the best you can to swing that probabilistic scale your way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Make Friends
I don’t care how good you are at your job or how lucky you are, no one will hire you if they don’t like you or they don’t know you. One of my supervisors and I were on a hiring panel together. I was on the panel to give advice and my supervisor was the final decision maker.  There were three candidates left and two were already working in our office.  When we were discussing the candidates the two from our office were both very qualified for the position.  However, neither of them had ever stepped foot into my supervisor’s office, even though they wanted the job. How can you expect to work with someone who avoids you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve heard it before and I’m going to say it again.  Network dammit!  If you are in a tie when it comes down to hiring, or your ranked slightly lower,  if the hiring official really likes you they will hire you. If they don’t like you or they don’t know you, you’re probably out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img sizes=&quot;100vw&quot; alt=&quot;My Dog George&quot; src=&quot;/images/post-images/permenant_job/g_salt_flats_large.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/permenant_job/g_salt_flats_large.jpg 1500w, /images/post-images/permenant_job/g_salt_flats_medium.jpg 1000w, /images/post-images/permenant_job/g_salt_flats_small.jpg 700w, /images/post-images/permenant_job/g_salt_flats_xsmall.jpg 500w&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;George, my dog, at the Bonneville Salt Flats near the UT, NV border. photo:me&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Never Give Up
When you are trying to get in, it isn’t going to be easy.  I’ve seen more than one person (so two) give up on a permanent job only to realize that giving up was a terrible decision. And by leaving and “trying something else” they put themselves back and made it harder to break into the permanent threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Diversify Your Portfolio
This is probably the most important suggestion in this post.  If you want to be a wildlife biologist, don’t just try to work with wildlife, work to diversify your skill set as much as possible.  Get really good at GIS, or range, or hydrology.  If you apply for a job where they need a wildlife bio that can do some hydrology, your in.  Getting that extra experience is easy too. With small underfunded field offices and districts it is really easy to get out and help other departments, especially if they have a little extra money. You will also potentially be able to get a permanent job with that department if a position opens. People will always hire someone that they know over someone who is unknown to them if you do a good job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Your Resume Needs to Be Perfect!
That’s right perfect, especially if the people doing the hiring don’t know you.  I used to hate this.  People make mistakes, I make them all the time (Yikes grammar is hard). But if you have one mistake in your Resume, I know a lot of people who will throw your resume away immediately.  It’s true, hiring should be done based on qualifications, but life ain’t (hehehe - its my blog) fair and when you have 800 candidates to get through, you are looking for any excuse to eliminate people. So make your resume perfect. Have everyone read it.  Your brother, sister, mother, father, friend, roommate, co-worker, neighbor, cat, hamster….everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Closing
In closing, getting a permanent federal job is by no means easy, but it can happen. And don’t look at the above suggestions as the sum total of all possibilities for getting a job.  They are suggestions from my experience.  Ask people that you work for and with or others who have gotten on-board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Good Luck!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2015/06/12/how-to-get-a-fed-job.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2015/06/12/how-to-get-a-fed-job.html</guid>
        
        <category>hiring</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Downloading R</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently went to a BLM training that was put on by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jornada.nmsu.edu/&quot;&gt;Jornada Research Station&lt;/a&gt;.  I was very impressed with how forward thinking they were in their approach to science. They were using wep apps, programming and technology in general to help them more efficiently do their jobs.  In their training they talked many times about using an open source software called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; to analyze data.  Being the computer geek that I am I had to download it.  Here’s  a quick tutorial on how I did it….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I use a mac at home and I downloaded R on my home machine.  I use a PC at work and if I get R working on my work machine I’ll update this tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##The Terminal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-image-icon center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/downloading-r/terminal-icon.png&quot; alt=&quot;R Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this work will be done inside the terminal. Terminal comes pre-installed with Mac OSX and can be found in your utilities folder. If you aren’t familiar with the terminal you should be.  Without going into too much detail the terminal allows you to do really cool things with your machine with short commands.  For example, you can run a server, open a program, create a file, access a remote surver, compile data, make a website, download programs and download and run R. For a short tutorial check &lt;a href=&quot;http://computers.tutsplus.com/tutorials/navigating-the-terminal-a-gentle-introduction--mac-3855&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-homebrew&quot;&gt;Get Homebrew&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used homebrew to install “r” and its dependencies on my machine.  If you don’t have homebrew, you can find a tutorial on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Homebrew/homebrew/blob/master/share/doc/homebrew/Installation.md#installation&quot;&gt;how to download it here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://brew.sh/&quot;&gt;what it is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;too-technical&quot;&gt;Too Technical?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also download R from a mirror at their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; if this all seems a little too technical (but come on, release your inner geek!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;download&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-image-icon center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/downloading-r/rlogo.png&quot; alt=&quot;R Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download, open up your terminal and type the following as individual commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;brew cask install xquartz
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;brew tap homebrew/science
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;brew install r
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;brew doctor
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its a good idea to check if everything installed correctly by typing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;r
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you should get the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;version&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;3.2.0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015-04-16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Full of Ingredients&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Copyright&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;The&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Foundation&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Statistical&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Computing&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Platform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x86_64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;darwin14.3.0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;free&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;software&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;comes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ABSOLUTELY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;NO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;WARRANTY.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;You&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;are&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;welcome&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;redistribute&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;it&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;under&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;certain&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;conditions.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;license()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;licence()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;distribution&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;details.&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Natural&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;support&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;but&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;running&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;an&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;English&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;locale&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;collaborative&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;project&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;many&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contributors.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;contributors()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;more&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;information&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;citation()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;how&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cite&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;packages&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;publications.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;demo()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;some&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;demos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;help()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;help&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;help.start()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;an&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;browser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;interface&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;help.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;q()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;quit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with R still running lets try a few things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;29000+30000&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;59000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s all there is to it, you have now downloaded R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Sublime Text&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/downloading-r/sublime-screen-shot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sublime Text 3 Screenshot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;Screen grab of my whole blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people can stop here.  You have R downloaded and you can start working with it.  However, if you enjoy improving you work environment like I do you can further improve your workflow if you want. I have really enjoyed using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sublimetext.com/&quot;&gt;Sublime Text 3&lt;/a&gt; as a text editor (an alternative to this would be to download &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rstudio.com/&quot;&gt;R Studio&lt;/a&gt;.  To bring R into an environment that I am familiar with, I downloaded &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wuub/SublimeREPL&quot;&gt;SublimeREPL&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;https://packagecontrol.io/&quot;&gt;Sublime Package control&lt;/a&gt;.  SublimeREPL allows you to compile R scripts right in the Sublime environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a key-binding in Sublime to run R scripts past the following into your Preferences&amp;gt;Key Bindings - User  file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
 // Executes a selection of text &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in &lt;/span&gt;REPL
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;keys&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;control+shift+j&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;command&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;repl_transfer_current&quot;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;args&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;scope&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;selection&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;,

// Executes the entire file &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;build&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in &lt;/span&gt;REPL
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;keys&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;control+shift+k&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;command&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;repl_transfer_current&quot;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;args&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;scope&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;file&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;,
   
// Executes line&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; of text &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in &lt;/span&gt;REPL terminal
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;keys&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;control+shift+l&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;command&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;repl_transfer_current&quot;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;args&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;scope&quot;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;lines&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can open sublime create a file like we did above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;29000+30000&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;59000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to Tools&amp;gt;SublimeREPL&amp;gt;R and an new window should pop up with the R warning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;version&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;3.2.0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015-04-16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Full of Ingredients&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Copyright&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;The&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Foundation&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Statistical&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Computing&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Platform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x86_64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;apple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;darwin14.3.0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;bit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;free&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;software&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;comes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ABSOLUTELY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;NO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;WARRANTY.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;You&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;are&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;welcome&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;redistribute&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;it&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;under&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;certain&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;conditions.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;license()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;licence()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;distribution&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;details.&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Natural&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;support&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;but&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;running&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;an&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;English&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;locale&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;collaborative&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;project&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;many&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contributors.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;contributors()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;more&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;information&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;citation()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;how&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cite&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;packages&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;publications.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;demo()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;some&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;demos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;help()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;help&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;help.start()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;an&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;browser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;interface&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;help.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;q()&#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;quit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;R.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you should be able to highlight your r text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;29000+30000&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;59000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and press cntrl+shift+j and your code should compile in the window running R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you’re ready to use or learn R in a very nice working environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Downloading and using Packages&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R takes advantage of packages to increase its flexibility. The packages are created by people to do specific things. For example let’s say I want to download a package that can do a power analysis for spacial information.  I search google and find that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/rSPACE/index.html&quot;&gt;rSPACE&lt;/a&gt; program does that.  I open up the command line and type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;install.packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&#39;rSPACE&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the command line will ask what mirror you would like to selact.  My closest is California, so I type “20”.  Note that downloading packages won’t work in REPL/Sublime if you have that set up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Including packages in a project&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this package in a script include the following at the beginning of the script to load the package into your project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rSPACE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that R libraries disappear at the end of each r session, so you must re-load the the library with each r session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More resources: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3RWb5U3X-T8&amp;amp;list=PLqzoL9-eJTNBDdKgJgJzaQcY6OXmsXAHU&amp;amp;index=11&quot;&gt;How to Package on Youtube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qPk0YEKhqB8&amp;amp;list=PLqzoL9-eJTNBDdKgJgJzaQcY6OXmsXAHU&amp;amp;index=4&quot;&gt;Video on how to use microsoft data in R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/doc/contrib/Seefeld_StatsRBio.pdf&quot;&gt;Stats for Biologists with R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alshum.com/sublime/&quot;&gt;How to get sublime text working with R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--  -----Links --------- --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2015/05/22/downloading-r.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2015/05/22/downloading-r.html</guid>
        
        <category>computer-science</category>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>statistics</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Endangered Species Act</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Endangered Species Act (ESA) is one fo the most successful conservation Acts in the United States. When challanged, the supreme court determined that the act was intended to &lt;em&gt;“halt and reverse the trend toward species exctinction, whatever the cost.”&lt;/em&gt;  Here’s an intro and a little history on the act that is both loved and hated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##History&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/bear-large.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 1001px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/bear-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 701px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/bear-small.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 500px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/bear-xsmall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Man vs the Wild&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;Grizzly bear - Listed as Threatened.  &lt;em&gt;Flickr Commons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 1900s, due to the extirpation of the passenger pigeon and the near disappearance of the American bison, extinction was introduced into the American lexicon. Over the next half century, the continued decline of several species due to pesticide use, hunting, collection and habitat degradation, kept the plight of species on the minds of the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1941, the whooping crane, a bird that ranged from central Canada south to Mexico, from Utah to the Atlantic coast, was reduced to just 16 birds in the wild. The whooping crane’s widespread disappearance received great attention at that time and helped gain support for species protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several laws that were passed that dealt with hunting and game animal management - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fws.gov/laws/lawsdigest/migtrea.html&quot;&gt;the Migratory Bird Treaty Act of 1918&lt;/a&gt;, a treaty prohibiting hunting right and gray whales, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bald_and_Golden_Eagle_Protection_Act&quot;&gt;Bald and Golden Eagle Protection Act of 1940&lt;/a&gt; - the mid 1960s saw the passage of laws that dealt with the conservation of species and their habitats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1966, the Preservation Act was passed by congress.   It  authorized &lt;a href=&quot;https://fws.gov&quot;&gt;US Fish and Wildlife Service&lt;/a&gt; the ability to list US species as endangered, and it allowed them to also spend up to $15 million per year to purchase habitat. The Act also expanded the Secretary of the Interior’s ability to purchase and manage the system of National Wildlife Refuges. In 1969, the act was amended to address the world wide trade and sale of species in danger of extinction, and strengthened the restrictions on the interstate commerce of species within the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/bison-large.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 1001px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/bison-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 701px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/bison-small.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 500px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/bison-xsmall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pen drawing of Bison&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;American Bison - Historic populations were thought to be in the tens of millions, American bison were hunted to near extinction in the early 1900, approximately 300 remained at that time. Due to conservation populations have recovered to the hundreds of thousands. &lt;em&gt;Flickr Commons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the passage of the Preservation Act, Richard Nixon, on December 28, 1973, signed the Endangered Species Act. It followed the passage of the Clean Water Act, the Clean Air Act and the the National Environmental Policy Act. The bones of the act required federal agencies to contribute to the conservation of listed species, as well as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prohibited the import, export or interstate or foreign sale of endangered and threatened animals and plants without a special permit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Made &lt;strong&gt;take&lt;/strong&gt; illegal – forbidding the killing, harming, harassing, pursuing, or removing the species from the wild.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Required federal agencies to conduct their activities to recover listed species.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Required federal agencies to consult (known as Section 7 Consultation) with the FWS to conserve listed species on federal actions that may harm listed species and only carry out activities that will not &lt;strong&gt;jeopardize&lt;/strong&gt; the survival of those species and their associated critical habitat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##ESA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fws.gov/international/pdf/esa.pdf&quot;&gt;ESA&lt;/a&gt; is only 49 pages and is made up of 18 Sections that lay out how the Service will make “Determination(s) of endangered and threatened species.” - Section 4; Penalties - Section 11; and “Interagency Cooperation” - Section 7. Interestingly in Section 2 the act provides a justification for its passage.  ESA states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“…various species of fish, wildlife, and plants in the United States have been rendered extinct as a consequence of economic growth and development untempered by adequate concern and conservation; (2) other species of fish, wildlife, and plants have been so depleted in numbers that they are in danger of or threatened with extinction; (3) these species of fish, wildlife, and plants are of aesthetic, ecological, educational, historical, recreational, and scientific value to the Nation and its people;…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Section 7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a biologist I deal with Section 7 of the act the most. Section 7 states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2) Federal agencies shall insure, through consultation, that federal actions are &lt;em&gt;“not likely to jeopardize the continued existence of any endangered species or threatened species or result in the destruction or adverse modification of habitat”&lt;/em&gt; of listed species.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(3) &lt;em&gt;“Federal Agencies shall consult with the Secretary on any prospective agency action at the request of, and in cooperation with prospective permit or license application if the applicant has reason to believe that the endangered or threatened species may be present in the area affected by his project and the implementation of such action will likely affect such species.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The section also lays out time frames for consultation, in formal cases it permits the FWS 90 Days once a consultation is submitted to reply with a biological opinion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Consultation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I intend to dedicate a whole blog post to Section 7 consultation.  However, you can’t write about ESA as a wildlife biologist without at least briefly touching on consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-image-icon center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/fws-logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fish and Wildlife Service Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Federal agencies are required to consult with FWS on any actions undertaken or permitted by them that “may affect” listed species or their critical habitat.  So the first determination that a biologist must make while reviewing a federal action, is to determine the level of affect that a project will have on listed species. This determination can result in a &lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;No Effect&lt;/strong&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;May affect, but not likely to adversely affect&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;May affect, and is likely to adversely affect&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; determination on species.  &lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;No effect&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; determinations do not require consultation with FWS, &lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;…not likely to adversely affect&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/em&gt;  determinations require informal consulation with the FWS - a 30 day process that results in a concurrence letter -, and &lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;…likely to adversely affect&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; determinations require formal consultation - a 90 day process that results in a Biological Opinion (BO) and incidental take permit if the service concurs that the project will not lead to jeopardy.  Determination of affects should be made based on the following definitions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;No Effect&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; means there will be no impacts, positive or negative, to listed or proposed resources. Generally, this means no listed resources will be exposed to the action and its environmental consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;May affect, but not likely to adversely affect&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; means that all effects are beneficial, insignificant, or discountable. Beneficial effects have contemporaneous positive effects without any adverse effects to the species or habitat. Insignificant effects relate to the size of the impact and include those effects that are undetectable, not measurable, or cannot be evaluated. Discountable effects are those extremely unlikely to occur. These determinations require written concurrence from the Service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;May affect, and is likely to adversely affect&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; means that listed resources are likely to be exposed to the action or its environmental consequences and will respond in a negative manner to the exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/pp-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 701px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/pp-small.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 500px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/esa/pp-xsmall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing of Passenger Pigeons&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;Drawing by: Louis Agassiz Fuertes - Passenger Pigeon, extinct 1914&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultations that lay out the analysis and rationale behind your effects determination are communicated in the form of a Biological Assessment (BA). A BA, as recommended by the Fish and Wildlife Services &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fws.gov/ENDANGERED/esa-library/pdf/esa_section7_handbook.pdf&quot;&gt;Consultation Handbook&lt;/a&gt;, should include the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction - Purpose of BA and Current Management Direction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consultation History&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proposed Management Actions and Alternatives Considered&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project Area Description&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Species Considered and Evaluated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluated Species Information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Environmental Baseline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effects to Evaluated Species and Determinations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effect Determination Summary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Additional Conservation Recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Literature Cited&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many nuances to consultation, how long it will take largely depends on how staffed the FWS is at the time and can take longer than listed in the act. Also, what you should include in your BA can depend largely on the individual assigned to your project at the FWS.  Some individuals prefer very detailed BAs, others prefer concise documents that only contain the very minimum amount of information to make a determination.  Although BAs should include &lt;em&gt;“the best available science”&lt;/em&gt;, their contents may vary and their creation is something of an art form. Sometimes when writing documents for the federal government it can be easy to get sucked into the &lt;em&gt;“I am just following a process”&lt;/em&gt; mentality. But it is important to remember the purpose of the act and use consultation to truly analyze project impacts to species and protect those species accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2015/05/22/esa.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2015/05/22/esa.html</guid>
        
        <category>Endangered</category>
        
        <category>Species</category>
        
        <category>USFS</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>NEPA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are a federal land manager, the holy grail of all statutes is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Environmental_Policy_Act&quot;&gt;National Environmental Policy Act of 1970&lt;/a&gt;, or NEPA, as most of us like to call it. So what exactly is NEPA and why is everyone always talking about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##History&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 1960s, due to several environmental catastrophes, the United States public started to pressure the federal government to pass legislation that protected the environment.  Over the next decade and a half several environmental statues were passed: Clean Air Act, Clean Water Act, Endangered Species Act and the National Environmental Policy Act, NEPA.  NEPA was enacted to help federally funded projects consider not just projects cost, efficiency, and development, but projects effects to the environment as well. The preamble lays out NEPA’s purpose nicely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;“To declare national policy which will encourage productive and enjoyable harmony between man and his environment; to promote efforts which will prevent or eliminate damage to the environment and biosphere and stimulate the health and welfare of man; to enrich the understanding of the ecological systems and natural resources important to the Nation…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;tldr: NEPA helps us prevent environmental damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/nepa/horse-large.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 1001px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/nepa/horse-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 701px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/nepa/horse-small.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 500px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/nepa/horse-xsmall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dry Cottonwood Creek Horse&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;Dry Cottonwood Creek Ranch Working Horses&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##What is NEPA?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever a federal action occurs, NEPA requires that we analyze that action’s affects on the natural environment. This allows both federal employees and the public to be informed of federal actions and allows for an inclusive planning process. Within the government, it requires biologists, ecologists, archaeologists, hydrologists, etc. to analyze effects of a project to the natural and cultural environment. And it requires the public to be informed of future actions and give them a chance to comment on actions before they are implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##How is it Done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do federal agencies have to do to comply with NEPA? All actions have to be analyzed and documented in one or more of the following documents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Environmental_Policy_Act#Preparation_of_a_Categorical_Exclusion&quot;&gt;Categorical Exclusion(CatEx)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are: &lt;em&gt;“a category of actions which do not individually or cumulatively have a significant effect on the human environment and which have been found to have no such effect in procedures adopted by a Federal agency…&lt;/em&gt; therefore, neither an environmental assessment nor an environmental impact statement is required._” (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/CFR-2010-title40-vol32/pdf/CFR-2010-title40-vol32-sec1508-4.pdf&quot;&gt;40 C.F.R. §1508.4&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environmental_impact_assessment#United_States&quot;&gt;Environmental Assessment (EA):&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; If a proposed action does not fall within CatEx, your first step in the NEPA process is an EA. Through environmental analysis in an EA, two outcomes can result: (a) a finding of no significant impact (FONSI), in which case the project may continue &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/retrieveECFR?gp=1&amp;amp;SID=3b36d48d544a2636ce097db169b41c9c&amp;amp;ty=HTML&amp;amp;h=L&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;r=PART&amp;amp;n=pt40.33.1508#se40.33.1508_19&quot;&gt;(40 CFR §1508.9)&lt;/a&gt;; or (b) you find that the action will lead to &lt;strong&gt;significant&lt;/strong&gt; impacts and further analysis is required in an:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environmental_impact_statement&quot;&gt;Environmental Impact Statement (EIS):&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are used to help make informed decisions on projects that will have &lt;strong&gt;significant&lt;/strong&gt; environemtal effects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##What is Significant?
During the course of taking various introductory NEPA courses, I really couldn’t figure out how to define significance.  And, being that one of the most important NEPA decision is to determine significance, it was frusturating to find that the threshold for significance was so ambigouse and difficult to figure out. So what do the regulations say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general to determine significance, you must consider both “context” and “intensity” of an action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/nepa/jtree-large.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 1001px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/nepa/jtree-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 701px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/nepa/jtree-small.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 500px)&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/nepa/jtree-xsmall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Joshua Tree in Joshua Tree National Park&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;Joshua Tree National Park&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context:&lt;/strong&gt; “This means that the significance of an action must be analyzed in several contexts such as society as a whole (human, national), the affected region, the affected interests, and the locality. Significance varies with the setting of the proposed action. For instance, for a site-specific action, significance would usually depend upon the effects in the locale rather than in the world as a whole. Both short-term and long-term effects are relevant.” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/retrieveECFR?gp=1&amp;amp;SID=3b36d48d544a2636ce097db169b41c9c&amp;amp;ty=HTML&amp;amp;h=L&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;r=PART&amp;amp;n=pt40.33.1508#se40.33.1508_127&quot;&gt;(40 CFR §1508.27)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intensity&lt;/strong&gt; “This refers to the severity of effect. Responsible officials must bear in mind that more than one agency may make decisions about partial aspects of a major action….” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/retrieveECFR?gp=1&amp;amp;SID=3b36d48d544a2636ce097db169b41c9c&amp;amp;ty=HTML&amp;amp;h=L&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;r=PART&amp;amp;n=pt40.33.1508#se40.33.1508_127&quot;&gt;(40 CFR §1508.27)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I get out of all of that is that “It depends”.  What I am coming to understand more and more is that NEPA is not always a clear path, but more often a helpful guide. After reading the CFRs I didn’t really understand how to come to a significance determination clearly. I did see a good example that helped me understand context and intensity better:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;“…let’s say a project would adversely affect 1 acre of salamander habitat. The impact would be significant if it were the last acre of habitat in the state, but would not be significant if there were a million acres of habitat in the state.” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ntc.blm.gov/krc/uploads/310/Lesson3_Significance-12-18-09.pdf&quot;&gt;(BLM NTC)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##What’s Important?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if significance is ambiguous, what is NEPA really for.  Well, I’m not really the one to ask but…. It seems like what is most important about NEPA is analyzing project effects and laying out your rationale for the decisions that you ultimately will make with that rationale. In other words, if you determine what effect your project will have on the human environment and then take that analysis and clearly explain how you came to a conclusion you are doing NEPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##In Closing
If there’s one thing that I’ve learned about NEPA its that its a hard topic to grasp completely without doing it a lot.  It always baffles me how almost everyone I ask interprets how to do NEPA correctly, differently.  So if you’re like me, and you have just started working on NEPA, hopefully you don’t get too wrapped up in the right or wrong way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Resources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Handbooks
* &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fs.fed.us/emc/nepa/includes/wo_1909_15_30.pdf&quot;&gt;Forest Service NEPA Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
* &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blm.gov/pgdata/etc/medialib/blm/wo/Information_Resources_Management/policy/blm_handbook.Par.24487.File.dat/h1790-1-2008-1.pdf&quot;&gt;BLM NEPA Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I am not a NEPA expert.  Far from it actually, if anyone out there is interested in contributing to this discussion that is a NEPA expert, I would love to hear from you or, even better, have you write a guest post. Contact me at schmidtyworks@gmail.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2015/05/11/NEPA.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2015/05/11/NEPA.html</guid>
        
        <category>NEPA</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chronicle I</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The chronicle is a short list of the tools that I’m using that help me do my job and some odds and ends that make life a little better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got this idea from Chris Coyier at &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com&quot;&gt;CSS-Tricks&lt;/a&gt;-  he’s on &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/css-tricks-chronicle-xx/&quot;&gt;Chronicle XX&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve learned a great deal about web workflow by reading his posts, and wanted to start doing the same for Biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Evernote&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-image-icon center img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/evernote-logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Evernote Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s one tool that I think every biologist should use it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://evernote.com/&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt;.  Evernote is awesome because it allows you to upload files and add tags to your notes to keep them organized.   I use it as a note taking, task tracking, annotated bibliography, file compiling juggernaut.  Check it out at:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/Registration.action&quot;&gt;account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/screenshot-gusglisting.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gunnison sage-grouse note from my evernote&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Google Calendar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-image-icon center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/calendar-icon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Calendar Icon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple of years I’ve really liked using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/calendar&quot;&gt;Google calendar&lt;/a&gt; to organize my life.  If you are like me and have several employees working on several different projects, Google calendar can help you lay out what needs to get done and, through your google account, the Calendar automatically shares that information with who ever you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/screenshot-calendar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Calendar Example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##iBird Pro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-image-icon center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-iphone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;iBird&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to find tools that are pushing our field forward. The suite of &lt;a href=&quot;http://ibird.com/&quot;&gt;iBird&lt;/a&gt; applications that are available for just about every tablet and smartphone platform are the ultimate bird guides for the 21st century.  Unlike a typical paper ID books, iBird comes with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A very nice search tool that allows you to search by habitat, bird size, shape and location.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every bird comes with a drawing and few pictures of the species. More common species usually include several morphs, juvenile as well as male female pictures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every bird comes with several call recordings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are even quizzes built in. So you can learn your calls and ID’s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Home Screen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-border img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
	&lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-home-large.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 800px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-home-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 550px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-home-small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ibird homescreen&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Images&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-border img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
	&lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-images-large.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 800px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-images-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 550px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-images-small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ibird homescreen&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Calls&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-border img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
	&lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-sound-large.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 800px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-sound-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 550px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/chronicle/ibird-sound-small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ibird homescreen&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2015/01/16/chronicle-I.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2015/01/16/chronicle-I.html</guid>
        
        <category>chronicle</category>
        
        <category>workflow</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Federal Hiring System</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I just applied for a new job with the federal government.  One week after applying for the position I was notified that I was “not referred” to the selecting officials for the position that I applied for with no justification. Fast forward two days later, for the same job, and after several phone calls and emails to human resources, I was referred to the hiring officials as one of the top candidates for the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After telling my story to others I was comforted to hear that I was not the only one that was baffled by the system.  The following is a collection of information that will hopefully prevent others from repeating my mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
	&lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/federal_hiring_system/city-of-rocks-big.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 900px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/federal_hiring_system/city-of-rocks-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 500px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/federal_hiring_system/city-of-rocks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;City of Rocks State Park | Photo: Mike Schmidt&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;City of Rocks State Park, Idaho. (Photo: Mike Schmidt)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Don’t Be Afraid to Call Human Resources
I heard over and over again that folks were having issues with hiring, but very few people had actually called HR.  If I hadn’t called HR I would never have been qualified for the job &amp;amp; my application would have been pointless.  The number on the job announcement is a good place to start.  However, don’t be afraid to call an HR person that you have worked with day to day.  They can often move you in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Merit vs DEU
There are two main types of announcements on USAjobs that you may apply for, DEU and Merit.  Merit announcements are open to applicants that are either currently working for the federal government in a career conditional or career appointment, or employees with status.  Typically if you are a current permanent federal employee you fall into one of these two categories (your most recent SF-50 should tell you as well). If you do not qualify for the Merit position then you can apply for the DEU position which is open to the the public.  It is very advantageous to qualify for Merit Positions.  When there are enough candidates that have applied for a Merit position, those that have applied for the DEU announcement will not even be considered. Unfortunately, not even a call or email to HR can help you at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;center excerpt light-grey max-width-700&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 class=&quot;center underline bold uppercase&quot;&gt;Merit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/hiring-merit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Merit description from USA jobs&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;center excerpt light-grey max-width-700&quot;&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;center underline bold uppercase&quot;&gt;DEU&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-images/hiring-deu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of DEU description from USA jobs&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##The Questionnaire
After you have chosen which job announcement is right for you, the first part of most applications consists of several questions that are supposed to asses how qualified you are for the job that you are applying for. Most of the multiple choice questions give you the option to select from the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have no experience in performing this work behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have limited experience in performing this work behavior. I have had exposure to this work behavior but would require additional guidance, instruction, or experience to perform it at a proficient level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have performed work in this task as a regular part of a job.  I have performed independently and normally without review by a supervisor or senior employee.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work in this task has been a central or major part of my job.  I have routinely performed the work and have trained others in performance of this work and others have consulted me as an expert for assistance in performance of this work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing: if you don’t rank high enough in the questionnaire, &lt;strong&gt;you will not be referred to the hiring official&lt;/strong&gt;, and no one will see your application.  Because of this fact, I have heard over and over again that you should just lie.  I don’t want to recommend that here. Lying applicants flood hiring certs with poor candidates, and that doesn’t help anyone.  Instead, the best thing that you can do to beat the questionnaire is to not &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fedsmith.com/2013/04/02/are-you-guilty-the-federal-jobseeker-and-deflating-questionnaire-responses/&quot;&gt;deflate&lt;/a&gt; your responses.  A good way to do this is to go through each question and right down a justification for each answer.  If you can justify, in any way, that the experiences that you have had fit in a higher category, then select it. Writing down a justification will also give you a reference if you get an interview.  Too many people take the questionnaire lightly and deflate their answers because they are afraid of being called out in an interview.  In my experience if someone is questioning the legitimacy of an answer you gave on the questionnaire, they want to eliminate you because they have another candidate in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
	&lt;picture class=&quot;full-width&quot;&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/federal_hiring_system/eastern-sierrabig.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 1000px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/federal_hiring_system/eastern-sierra-medium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 800px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/post-images/federal_hiring_system/eastern-sierra.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eastern Sierra Mountains, Bishop, California | Photo: Mike Schmidt&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;Inyo National Forest in Bishop, California. (Photo: Mike Schmidt)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Education&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was notified by USA Jobs that I was not referred, it didn’t tell me why. I had assumed that it was because I had not submitted the correct documentation, or not rated high enough compared to the other candidates.  So, and because of habit, I called HR to figure out what “not referred” meant and why I was put in that category. Turns out my application was junked because I was supposedly missing one educational credit in plant biology. Strangely, I had recently been qualified for the exact same position by another HR department.  What happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most series have an educational component that you must meet to be referred to hiring officials. My qualifications looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least 9 semester hours in such wildlife subjects as mammalogy, ornithology, animal ecology, wildlife management, or research courses in the field of wildlife biology; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least 12 semester hours in zoology in such subjects as general zoology, invertebrate zoology, vertebrate zoology, comparative anatomy, physiology, genetics, ecology, cellular biology, parasitology, entomology, or research courses in such subjects (Excess courses in wildlife biology may be used to meet the zoology requirements when appropriate.); and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At least 9 semester hours in botany or the related plant sciences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you submit your application an HR person goes through all of the candidates and checks to see which candidates have the correct courses to qualify for a job. In my case, and depending on the HR person, Ecology can count as a plant science (as was the case for me with the Forest Service) or not (as was the case with the BLM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pleaded with HR “I promise you, that class was 2 weeks of plant and 2 weeks of animal research techniques”.  You can understand their reluctance to believe me.  I even went as far as to send her the definition of ecology.  But, alas, she would not budge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t let this happen to you&lt;/strong&gt; - I was told that the only way they would accept my course without additional verifiable information, was if the title of the course had “Animal” or “Plant” in the title. To avoid this fiasco, submit additional information with your education in the section that asks for additional attachments at the end of the questionnaire.  For me all I had to do was send them a copy of the course description from my college course catalog and they accepted Ecology as a plant science. I was also told that a signed letter on official letterhead would also work (this would have applied to my research on plants in “Senior Thesis”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Be Nice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HR folks get yelled at all the time for doing the best they can at a task that should not be assigned to them, &lt;strong&gt;BE NICE&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2014/10/01/Navigating-The-Federal-Hiring-System.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2014/10/01/Navigating-The-Federal-Hiring-System.html</guid>
        
        <category>hiring</category>
        
        <category>feds</category>
        
        <category>USAjobs</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why am I Blogging?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my first blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://schmidtyworks.com&quot;&gt;schmidtyworks.com&lt;/a&gt;.  That being the case, I wanted to make some goals for this site and layout why I’ve decided to put my hat in the blogging ring. First a little bit of background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Learning Web Design&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past two and a half years I’ve slowly been digging myself deeper into the world of web design.  I’ve learned a lot.  Enough to build this site from scratch with state of the art tools that were mostly free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never taken a single class in computer programming or design. What I’ve learned has come from some amazing and free online resources. &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com&quot;&gt;CSS-Tricks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.tutsplus.com&quot;&gt;tuts+&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://treehouse.com&quot;&gt;Treehouse&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://timothytraining.net&quot;&gt;Timothy Training&lt;/a&gt;, to name a few of the major ones.  Most of the sites that I learned from are either made by one person, CSS-Tricks for example (he has guests occasionally), or are a curated collection of many individuals articles. Regardless, web designers and developers are encouraged to share what they’ve learned and how they learned it. Thus creating a WEB of shared knowledge and experiences for the betterment of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##For Me, Web Development is Just a Hobby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building websites is my hobby.  Managing public lands as a biologist is my career.  In biology we don’t share much. What we do, is shared in a scientific journal, very long PDF or email.   While these are amazing sources of information, they are hard to read and usually really boring.  My dream is to have a resource where people can go and learn the way that web designers do.  I can’t tell you how many times that I have googled something biological and come up with an endless stream of PDFs.  One day I want to google Mexican Spotted Owl Surveys and read a blog post about what issues people ran into and what they’ve learned instead of a 20 page &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fws.gov/mountain-prairie/endspp/protocols/MexicanSpottedOwlSurveyProtocol2012.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;. We have the internet now.  Make it interactive, responsive and community based. We can do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-box-shadow-effect&quot;&gt;
	&lt;picture&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;video style=&quot;display: none;&quot;&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/castletontowerlarge.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 1000px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;source srcset=&quot;/images/castletontowermedium.jpg&quot; media=&quot;(min-width: 800px)&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;!--[if IE 9]&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;
		&lt;img srcset=&quot;/images/castletontowersmall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Castleton Tower | Photo: Mike Schmidt&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;photo-tag&quot;&gt;Some of the most beautiful public lands around.  Castleton Tower, Castle Valley, Utah. (Photo: Mike Schmidt)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Where Are You Going With This? 
I care deeply about public land management.  Some of my favorite places in the world are on public lands, and I am fortunate to have the privilege to manage them.  But, I have so much to learn.  Sharing what I am working on in a way that makes sense to someone else is the best way to actively learn something in my opinion.  Learning and teaching is great, but the real beauty of this system of teaching/learning will, hopefully, build a resource that is useful to myself and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.martinfenner.org/2014/08/25/using-microsoft-word-with-git/&quot;&gt;Others are already doing this (not really biology related, but helpful in my field nonetheless)&lt;/a&gt; and I’m sure there are more people beginning to share then I realize.  So I want to do my part by sharing my experiences on this blog.  Hopefully I’ll learn a lot along the way and create a resource that is useful not just for me, but for those that come after me as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Winter 2014 Goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finish the site.&lt;/strong&gt;  I still have a lot to do, so I’m going to start simple.  Home page will be my most recent article.  Article page will be an archive page. My Web page will be Web stuff (gotta give back). About page will be about (duh). As of this writing I just have a home page.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start collecting things that I’ve learned by doing my job.&lt;/strong&gt; I want to write about what I’ve been working on and learning at work. Hopefully when I’m done I will have a really good resource for myself at the very least.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add a comments Section to the site.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a lot for the rest of the year.  At the beginning of the year I’ll check back in and make some adjustments if need be.  So, here’s to a beginning!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>//blog/2014/09/24/Why-am-i-blogging.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//blog/2014/09/24/Why-am-i-blogging.html</guid>
        
        <category>science</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
